בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is ל"א, Lamed Aleph, and
we have a great sort of self-contained, well I don't know self-contained,
but anyway, a great discussion that will cover this whole דף, daf,
get us up up to the משנה Mishnah on the next דף,
daf, and this is a continuation of the earlier issues about a
person who trips and people get damaged by him or get damaged
by something that he breaks, and we're going to actually have the
case of a multi-car backup, multi-car not backup, multi-car collision, okay? That
one car gets into an accident with another car and then another
with the second and the third with the fourth and so on,
and then it'll lead to these whole questions about exactly who is
liable. But the other question that it also gets to is, right,
the degree of negligence in terms of tripping and also creating when
you damage other people, אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik versus a בור. Bor.
So a lot of very sort of like interesting issues we've been
discussing coming in application in this particular case. So let's take a
look at this משנה. Mishnah. Top of ל"א עמוד א'. Lamed Aleph
Amud Aleph. שני קדרין שהיו
מהלכין זה אחר זה. Shenei Kadarin she-hayu mehalchim zeh achar zeh. So
two potters, thank you, that were walking one behind the other. ונתקל
הראשון ונפל. V-nitkal harishon ve-nafal.
And the first one tripped and fell.
And so that's, you know, the whole discussion about נתקל פושע Nitkal
Poshea or not פושע poshea or so on. I think this is
the first time that the משנה Mishnah uses the word נתקל. Nitkal.
Right beforehand it spoke about the pot breaking and so on. Here
finally it describes the act of tripping. The first one tripped and
fell down. ונתקל השני בראשון. Ve-nitkal hasheni barishon. And the second one
tripped over the first one. הראשון חייב בנזקי השני. Harishon chayav benezkei
hasheni. The first guy is liable for the damages to the second,
to the second. Okay, so this is simple sense. Presumably he's negligent.
Or actually, as we've been pointing out, you know, the משניות Mishnayot
until now have been a little frustrating because they do not really,
they talk about different scenarios, about a pitcher breaking, about
somebody intentionally spilling the water and so on. Anyway, the common theme
is that the guy who created the hazard is always liable, but
it never exactly tells you what the degree of negligence is that's
required. But the גמרא's Gemara been asserting that, you know, that it's
not a total אונס. ones. Why should you be חייב chayav if
you're an אונס? ones? If you made a בור, Bor, you need
a certain degree of negligence. It's always been assuming in the משניות
Mishnayot that there is negligence. Here you have the guy who tripping,
so presumably that's telling you that tripping has that minimum degree of
negligence required. So let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara
says. אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yochanan. Says רבי יוחנן. Rabbi Yochanan.
לא תימא מתניתין רבי מאיר היא דאמר נתקל פושע הוא. Lo tema
matnitin Rabbi Meir hi de-amar nitkal poshea hu. Don't say our משנה
Mishnah is רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir hi, who says that one who
trips is negligent, right? That's going back to that earlier משנה Mishnah
about the pitcher that breaks. That the גמרא Gemara that רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir says you're חייב chayav and רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says
only if you're intentional, and the classic way the גמרא Gemara framed
that debate was whether tripping is פושע, poshea, although that wasn't about
tripping, that was about a pitcher that broke. But anyway, here you
see why we're framing it as tripping, because this משנה's Mishnah about
tripping.
אלא אפילו רבנן דאמרי אונס הוא. Ela afilu Rabbanan de-amri ones hu.
Even the רבנן Rabbanan that say that somebody who trips over his
own two feet is considered to be an אונס ones or at
least not a פושע. poshea. ופטור, Upatur, and normally you'd be פטור
patur if you tripped and broke a pot and the pot created
a hazard. Here you're going to be חייב. chayav. הכא חייב. Hacha
chayav. Why are you חייב? chayav? שהיה לו לעמוד ולא עמד. She-hayah
lo la'amod velo amad.
Because you should have stood up and you didn't stand up. So
this is just, you know what this is just like? This is
just like you trip באונס be-ones and you don't pick up, you
have time to pick up your broken pot and you don't pick
it up. So we said there that you'd be חייב, chayav, because
you are supposed to remove it and pick up your pot even
if the pot broke באונס. be-ones. The only possible exception would be
is if you were מפקיר mafkir the pot after it broke, so
then it's not your responsibility. But after you trip, you're not being
מפקיר mafkir yourself, okay?
You still are always responsible for yourself even if you trip. So
once you have a chance to get up and you don't get
up, that's where the liability occurs. שהיה לו לעמוד ולא עמד. She-hayah
lo la'amod velo amad. Yes? Is it because of אדם המזיק Adam
HaMaziq or because of בור? Bor?
Excellent, so that is going to be, that was the question I
was going to raise, that is going to be a central question
in the discussion, right? Here's the issue.
We said that let's say you don't need any negligence. If a
wind were to push me on top of you or on top
of your pot and I or whatever, your pitcher and I broke
it, I'd be חייב, chayav, אדם מועד לעולם. Adam Muad L'Olam.
Okay, but here I am stationary, you are tripping on me, and
you are maybe even breaking your pot even if it broke directly
on my body, on my person. Is that an act of אדם
המזיק? Adam HaMaziq? because it was broke on my body, or is
that an act of בור bor, *bor* because ultimately it was not
me impacting your pitcher, but your pitcher impacting me? And that is
a really key question about whether you view this case of me
being an obstacle and tripping and breaking something on me, is that
an אדם המזיק adam hamazik. *adam hamazik* or is that a בור
bor *bor*? If it's a בור bor *bor*, you understand why you
need negligence. Why do you say היה לו לעמוד haya lo la'amod,
ולא עמד *haya lo la'amod v'lo amad*? But if it's an אדם
המזיק adam hamazik. *adam hamazik*, you don't understand why you should need
negligence. In the end of the day, I broke my pitcher on
you, right? אדם adam *adam* is מועד לעולם *muad l'olam*. So this
would seem to indicate either that that case of me tripping over
a person, the person is a בור bor *bor*, or the position
of תוספות Tosfos *Tosafot* that even אדם המזיק adam hamazik. *adam hamazik*
requires a certain degree of negligence. Now I can just tell you
parenthetically, not to complicate it, but there's a way that you can
make it אדם המזיק adam hamazik *adam hamazik* even according to the
רמב"ן Ramban *Ramban* that you don't need negligence and say here you
have to say that I should have stood because it is combining
the idea of the negligence with defining it as an action. Meaning,
if I am stationary, it's sort of like this is exactly the
thing that's going to determine am I a בור bor *bor* or
an אדם המזיק adam hamazik *adam hamazik*. If I'm stationary, stationary and
I had no opportunity yet to stand and you tripped on me,
then I'm a בור bor *bor*. It's not my act at all.
You did something against my body, I'm a בור bor *bor*. But
as soon as I could have stood and I didn't stand, that
inserts the aspect of agency, right? Do you understand? That means that
I'm essentially choosing to remain here. And as soon as you insert
agency and I'm choosing to remain here and then you break something
on me, then it's like I broke the thing because I made
that choice. So even if in terms of the physics of the
thing, I fell and broke something, even though I didn't make a
choice, a wind pushed me over, that's an אדם המזיק adam hamazik.
*adam hamazik*. But if the physics is that you broke it on
me, we can still turn it into an אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik.
*adam hamazik* because I made the choice to be here and that
makes it like I did something. So it's a fascinating three active
different ways of defining what this scenario is. Either you just say
it's always בור bor *bor*, physically I'm being passive and that's why
you need negligence. Or you say it's always אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik.
*adam hamazik* because my body came in contact with it and this
shows that אדם המזיק Adam Hamazik *adam hamazik* needs a certain degree
of negligence. Or you say whether it's בור bor? *bor* or אדם
המזיק adam hamazik *adam hamazik* is a function of whether I was
making a choice or not. Okay? If I was stationary and not
making a choice, I'm a בור bor *bor*. But if I was
stationary and choosing to be here, then I'm like actively being here,
then I'm an אדם המזיק adam hamazik, *adam hamazik*. Yes.
In practical terms, is there going to be a dispute determining
the
timing?
Yeah, well sure. I mean, who's the one that's going to determine
it? And are we going to have some rule of thumb, ten
seconds, one minute? And then who's going to assess, well that's your
rule of thumb, but these cases were different because of this and
that? Right? There's always the question that the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* tends
to ignore, which is the determining of the facts, right? Half of
any legal case is always not the law, question of the law,
but the determining of the facts. Right? So that's a very good
question.
Does it make any difference at all to this case if the
second one damaged the first one too?
We're going to get to that. I'm not going to get to
that yet exactly, but we're going to get to something similar, of
the second one damaging the third. Okay? But yeah, I mean if
the second also tripped and damaged the second, then that wouldn't affect
the first one's liability, but that would be looked at through its
own lens as the second guy's אדם המזיק adam hamazik *adam hamazik*.
Okay, so גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this.
Okay, שהיה לו לעמוד La'amod, ולא עמד *shehaya lo la'amod v'lo amad*.
רב Rav נחמן בר יצחק אמר *Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar*, אפילו
afilu תימא לא lo, היה לו לעמוד haya lo la'amod. *afilu teima
lo haya lo la'amod*, even if you didn't have time to stand
up, היה Haya לו להזהיר ולא הזהיר *haya lo lehazhir v'lo hizhir*,
your liability comes that you should have warned the guy, watch out,
I'm on the ground! Okay? So everybody agrees that you need a
certain degree of negligence. Okay, again, either again because it's בור bor.
*bor* and you need negligence or because אדם המזיק adam hamazik *adam
hamazik* needs negligence or you could need the negligence to turn him
into an אדם המזיק adam hamazik, *adam hamazik*, whatever the case is.
And but they're saying you don't need the negligence in the tripping.
The negligence could come from the not standing or the negligence could
come from the not warning. Okay?
It could be a different amount of time.
Exactly, exactly. That's exactly the point. רבי יוחנן אמר *Rabbi Yochanan amar*,
no. כיון דלא היה לו לעמוד haya lo la'amod *keivan d'lo haya
lo la'amod*, since he did not have either the ability or the
time, presumably the time to stand, לא היה לו להזהיר *lo haya
lo lehazhir*, you cannot say that he should have warned, איטריד *iterid*,
he is distracted, right? He is preoccupied. Here he is, he's fallen
down, it's like oh my knee, my knee, whatever. So how are
you going to say, oh while you're in pain about your knee,
how much do we make you responsible to be warning the guy
who's coming? And how much as you're trying to get up, as
I'm trying to get myself together and to stand up, so I
have to also be aware that somebody might be coming behind me
and warning? Right? That's a very interesting question, right? Like how much
are we reasonable in saying that when you're in pain or you
fell or whatever, we entitle you to be focused or it's natural
to be focused on taking care of yourself and we can't impose
on you a responsibility to be concerned about others or do we
say no, you... Always have to be concerned about other people that
might get damaged by you, you know. So that's a really interesting
question. So that's the debate of if you didn't yet have time
to stand up, do you still have time to do you are
you still responsible to warning others during those circumstances? Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara says: תנן, Tnan, let's take a look. So the
משנה Mishna says, not this משנה, Mishna, but the משנה Mishna we're
about to come up to. היה בעל קורה ראשון ובעל חבית אחרון.
Haya baal kora rishon ubaal chavit acharon.
So the guy with the beam, the guy with the beam is
walking in front of a guy with a barrel. Okay, so if
a beam comes you ever play rock paper scissors? Okay, so rock
always beats scissors, okay? So the beam always beats the barrel. The
guy with the beam is walking in front of the guy with
a barrel, okay? היה now, היה בעל קורה ראשון, haya baal kora
rishon, so the guy
so he's first, ובעל חבית אחרון, ubaal chavit acharon, the guy with
the barrel or pitcher is behind him. נשברה חבית בקורה. Nishbara chavit
bekora.
So the guy with the barrel or the pitcher went too
fast and sped up and banged his pitcher into the guy's beam,
so פטור. patur. So of course the guy with the beam is
exempt, like you know, you did it to yourself. ואם עמד, Vim
amad,
but if he stood, בעל קורה חייב. baal kora chayav. The guy
with the beam is חייב chayav because he is the one that
was negligent. Everybody is walking and like if you stop in the
middle of the highway, right, then you know, you're to blame, you
know, you have to keep on going. That's the rules of the
road, okay?
He should've gone along.
But if you stop in the middle of the highway and somebody
crashes into you, they're liable?
The person behind is generally liable.
Everybody's going sixty miles an hour, you stop, you're liable?
If you stop for a good reason, yeah. No, no, if you
stop
in the middle of the highway it doesn't matter, the guy behind
is supposed to be
in control of his car. But this is too sudden.
Okay,
he's supposed to be in enough stopping distance. Oh, that's oh, that's
an interesting point. So is this assuming that's a good question. But
also I wonder whether this is with the question here about visibility.
Here I am, I'm carrying a barrel or whatever, what's the presumed
what can we presume about the visibility issue? All right, those are
good questions. We'll discuss that more when we get to the next
משנה, Mishna, that's tomorrow. Okay, now by the way, the other point
I should make that תוספות Tosafot makes is that this shows you
that I could be stationary and an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. Why?
Because if I stop and I'm a if you consider me to
be a בור, bor so then I'm
פטור בכלים. patur bekelim. Why? Because you know, because a בור bor.
is פטור בכלים. patur bekelim. So maybe because it was my beam,
it's not me. But anyway, okay, so this already starts and the
act of stopping. Anyway, but here at least you have a case,
presumably
why are you?
Because you're not, because presumably you're אדם המזיק. adam hamazik, Okay, or
you could say maybe you want to say the beam is a
whatever, but this is a key question that runs through this, whether
a stopped person is a בור bor. or an אדם המזיק. adam
hamazik, Okay, anyway, so it says: ואם עמד בעל הקורה חייב. Vim
amad baal hakora chayav. If you stop then you're liable. מאי לאו,
Mai lav, now, what we're going to focus on is where is
it about your liability? Actually this is exactly the question. Did you
have a right to stop? And if you did have a right
to stop, and the guy should be anticipating you might stop, why
are you liable? Okay, so actually very similar to the point that
Charlie just made. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי לאו, Mai lav,
are we not talking
שעמד לכתף, sheamad lekatef, that you actually stopped in order to switch
your shoulders, you know, to adjust it on your shoulder, which is
a normal thing that people do, דאורחיה הוא, deorechei hu, it's a
normal thing. So there's a guy behind you, should have like you
know, should have maybe anticipated that that might have happened. So then
why are you liable? וקתני חייב. Uktani chayav. Why are you liable?
דהוה ליה להזהיר, Dehavei lei lehazhir, that maybe because we would say
even if the guy behind you should to some degree have been
paying attention, okay, you nevertheless have a greater responsibility to warn. You
know, it always depends on who do we put the primary responsibility
on. So if we say yes, you're allowed to stop to adjust,
but when you're doing that, thank you, you have to be you
know, you have to be aware people might be behind you and
you have to yell out a warning, okay? So that type of
a case, so that would explain why you'd be חייב, chayav, that
even though it's a normal thing to do, you still have that
responsibility. And that would show you, presumably, the גמרא Gemara is making
an analogy, that presumably if we say that while you're switching the
shoulder of your beam, adjusting it on your shoulder, you still have
to be and you're focused on your own sort of issue, you
still have to be paying attention to what's going on around you
and warn people. So by analogy, even after you fell down and
you're focused on standing up, you would still have to be warning
people around you. Now I think there's a little bit of a
difference. In one case it's an accident, I'm overwhelmed, right, I gotta
actually whatever, so there's, you know, but nevertheless the גמרא Gemara is
making that analogy. So if you need to warn somebody by adjusting
their load, when you're adjusting the load, you should be warning somebody
while you're trying to stand up. So the גמרא Gemara says: מאי
לאו שהיה לו להזהיר, Mai lav shehaya lo lehazhir, לא, כשעמד לפוש.
Kesheamad leafush. I'm sorry, no. He was not just standing to adjust,
he actually stood to take a break. It's like there I was,
you said if I have a good reason to stop
in the middle of the
highway... If you want to take a break, you pull over to
the shoulder, okay? So if you're just doing it for a completely
not justifiable reason and you're doing something that is not expected and
not normally allowed or whatever, then you're liable even if you don't
have an opportunity to warn people. You're fundamentally liable for making that
choice of stopping in the middle of the highway.
Note the גמרא Gemara doesn't say the other guy damages you. That's
the other question, then is he liable?
Presumably not, פשיטא הניזק כל המשנה באחר ושינה בו פטור. Pshita hanizak
kol hamishaneh b'acher v'shinah bo potur. Okay, so it says, שושיינא? Shoshana?
No, כשעמד לפוש. K'she'amad lafush. So the גמרא Gemara says like this:
אבל עמד לכתף מאי? Aval amad l'kateif mai?
So what now? Now, by the way, though, and here I'm surprised
you didn't ask this, Charlie, תוספות Tosafot says, I don't get it.
If you're the guy driving behind him and we're saying that you're
responsible that, you know, people will often stop in the middle of
the road to adjust their beam and therefore you have to be
on the lookout and therefore you're going to be liable if somebody
does that because you have to be being aware that might happen
and being prepared to adjust yourself accordingly. So תוספות Tosafot says, well
then at the end of the day, what difference does it make
why he stopped? I'm supposed to be anticipating that he might stop,
so even if he stopped for a not good reason, I should
be responsible to, you know, to avoid him. So תוספות Tosafot, gives
some answer, but I just want—but you know, but the question—you can
look at it—the question I think is a little more interesting than
the answer. The answer I think could be is that there's always
like different degrees of liability. That's true, in general we say you
should be watching out. And should you have anticipated that he stopped
and adjusted because it doesn't matter why he stopped? Yes. But his
liability is still greater because he had no right to be stopping
without a legitimate reason. So you know, it's not denying that you
maybe also should have been anticipating and adjusting, but fundamentally he had
no right to stop in the middle of the highway, you know,
then he is liable.
I think also it depends on how suddenly he stopped.
Well, that's also, right.
There's a lot of factors here. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
anyway, so it says, no, he stopped without any good reason. He
stopped just to take a break. You don't take a break in
the middle of the highway. You move off to the side. And
that's why you're liable. But if he stopped to adjust his load,
we do not require or say that he should at that time
be warning people. So the גמרא Gemara. says, אבל עמד לכתף מאי?
Aval amad l'kateif mai? So what would you say if he stood
to just adjust his load? פטור? Potur? He'd be exempt because he
doesn't have to warn people while he's doing that, because that's, you
know, it's not reasonable to expect that of him. If that's true,
עד דתני סיפא, Ad d'tani seifa, the end of the משנה Mishnah
teaches, ואם אמר לו לבעל חבית עמוד פטור. Ve'im amar lo l'ba'al
chavit amod potur.
If he says to the guy with the pitcher behind him, stand,
stop! I'm about—I just stopped. You stop! Like he warns the guy,
it explicitly says if he warns the guy, he's exempt. ליפלוג ולתני
בדידיה. Liflog u'litni b'dideih. Why not make a distinction in the case
itself? במה דברים אמורים כשעמד לפוש. Bameh devarim amurim k'she'amad lafush. When
are you חייב Chayav when you stop to just take a break,
a breather. אבל עמד לכתף פטור, Aval amad l'kateif potur, but if
you stop to adjust, פטור Potur you're exempt even if you didn't
warn the guy. Like that's a bigger חידוש Chiddush that you can
stop and—it's not such a חידוש Chiddush to say that if you
warn the guy you're exempt. It's a bigger חידוש Chiddush to say
that you're exempt if you were just adjusting your load. So the
גמרא Gemara says, no, this is still a חידוש Chiddush this way.
הא קמשמע לן דאף על גב דעמד לפוש, Ha kamashma lan d'af
al gav d'amad lafush, even if you stood to take a break,
כי אמר לו לבעל חבית עמוד פטור. Ki amar lo l'ba'al chavit
amod potur. You satisfy your responsibility when you tell the guy to
stop. You might think it is such a violation to just stop
in the middle of the highway, right? I'm just imagining this, right?
Everybody's going sixty miles an hour. You're stopping in the middle lane
to check
your emails.
I'm just
stopping
to take a break. I need to check my emails. Oh, but
I said—I don't know—I put on my hazards, I put on my
blinkers. So no, maybe that is such a violation and so irresponsible
that even if you warn the guy you're going to be liable.
קמשמע לן Kamashma lan that you're not. Okay, so this is like
a really interesting question. Like, I appreciate that because I would, you
know, that the sort of parallel to the contemporary issues. If you're
stopping, how much is that considered to be acceptable? Do you have
a right to do that? Something to be anticipated? etc. And when
you are doing—or if it's something completely you shouldn't be doing then
obviously you have more absolute liability. But how much also when you
are taking care of something that's reasonable to do, like getting yourself
up from having fallen down or adjusting your load, which is what
people do, how much of that time can we obligate you to
be warning people behind you? And if we can be obligating you
and you're not, you're liable, but if it's not reasonable to ask
you to be paying attention to other people at that time, then
you're going to be—then you will be exempt, okay? Either you'll be
an אונס, Oness, in our case of the משנה Mishnah you fell
down, you're an אונס, Oness, or it'll be something that becomes their
responsibility to watch out for. If people have a right to adjust
their load and they're not expected to warn people, then that creates
a greater responsibility for me who is walking behind people to know
that this type of a thing might happen and for me to
be careful and for me to be on the lookout.
Yes, this—our משנה Mishnah because that says המשתנה ושינה זה בזה פטור...
Hamishatneh v'shinah zeh bazeh potur... According to that opinion that says שאין
דרך בני אדם להתבונן בדרכים, she'ein derech b'nei adam l'hitbonen badrachim, but
the other people that before made it like oh אפילו whatever it
is, that wouldn't work too well with—
No, because that's exactly what the גמרא's Gemara. the first line of
the גמרא. Gemara First of all, here the phrase we uses נתקע
פושע. nitzka poshea. שאין דרך בני אדם להתבונן בדרכים she'ein derech b'nei
adam l'hitbonen badrachim
is when you actually trip over something. When you trip over your
own two feet, that's considered a discussion of נתקע. nitzka. Okay, but
this is exactly what the גמרא Gemara said. Even if your tripping
is an אונס, ones, your liability is cause you should've gotten up
or because assuming that you had the time to get up. Or
your liability is you should've warned, and that's the debate. Are you
liable if you didn't have the time to get up, but you
had the time to warn somebody? So that's exactly what we're saying.
Doesn't matter why you fell. That's exactly the first line of the
גמרא. Gemara Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this. תא
שמע. ta shema. Okay. תא
שמע. ta shema. Come and hear.
הקדרים והזגגים. hakadarim v'hazagagim.
So the potters and the glass blowers or the glass sellers, okay,
שהיו מהלכין זה אחר זה, shehayu mahalchin ze achar ze, were walking
one behind the other. נתקל הראשון ונפל. nitkal harishon v'nafal. The first
guy tripped and fell down. ונתקל השני בראשון. v'nitkal hasheni barishon. Here
you get your multi-car pile-up. Okay. The second guy tripped over the
first guy. והשלישי בשני, v'hashlishi basheni, and the third guy tripped over
the second guy. ראשון חייב בנזקי שני ושני חייב בנזקי שלישי. rishon
chayav b'nizkei sheni v'sheni chayav b'nizkei shlishi. First one is liable for
the second, the second is liable for the third. So the question
is, why is the second liable for the third, right? He was
אונס, ones, he could've whatever. So we'll see if he actually had
a chance, opportunity to warn, right? If he didn't, it happened immediately,
he'd be פטור. patur. But but if he had the opportunity to
get up or he had an opportunity to warn or whatever. But
that's not being spelled out in this ברייתא. braita. This ברייתא braita
just says second guy's liable for the third guy.
Okay. ראשון חייב בנזקי שני ושני חייב בנזקי שלישי. rishon chayav b'nizkei
sheni v'sheni chayav b'nizkei shlishi. ואם מחמת ראשון נפלו. v'im machmat rishon
naflu. If they all fell because of the first guy, directly because
of the first guy. Okay, the גמרא's Gemara going to say what
that means is the first guy let's say is carrying a beam
and he falls and his beam goes across the whole road. So
then everybody who comes after him, two, three, four, they don't bump
trip into the guy before them, they all trip over the same
beam. Okay, so if everybody behind him directly trips over the first
guy, okay, or the first guy's beam or whatever it might be,
then חייב בנזקי כולם, chayav b'nizkei kulam, he is liable for all
of that. By the way, that's the way the גמרא Gemara is
going to interpret it. You could've said what it means is it's
because of the first, means that the second and the third guy
did not have a chance to get up or warn. So if
they, right? I mean, what would be the story there in terms
of just civil liability? One guy is negligent and crashes his car
and then two crashes into one and three into two whatever. Is
one liable for everybody's?
No, I think each one is presumed to, you know, have enough
distance to be able to—
Oh, that gets back to Charlie's point about that you should've had
stopping distance or whatever. Oh, that com— that complicates, right. Okay.
All right. So anyway, but but what you could've said, wait, we
haven't, the גמרא Gemara hasn't done anything yet, so far it's what's
in the ברייתא. braita. What you could've said was what it meant
that if guy two could've warned or stood up, he's liable for
guy three. But if there was not not no opportunity, it happened
too quickly, then it's all number one's fault. Okay, but that's not
how the גמרא's Gemara going to say. The גמרא's Gemara going to
say that last line where number one is to be liable for
everyone, it's when they all directly tripped over number one.
And what's נתקל השלישי בשני nitkal hashlishi basheni then? It's not true
if they all fall over one.
No, no, then it's describing a different scenario. I understand. That's what
I said. The sim— an easier read of "it's all because of
the first guy" means that he's to blame but because the other
people didn't have a chance to do anything about it. Okay, but
we're not going to focus on that last case, although that is
I think equally interesting. Okay, we're first going to focus on the
first case where one is liable for two, two for three, etc.,
and try and understand why that's going to be. Okay, so one
minute. ואם מחמת ראשון נפלו חייב בנזקי כולם. v'im machmat rishon naflu
chayav b'nizkei kulam. ואם הזהירו זה את זה פטורים. v'im hizhiru ze
et ze pturim.
But if two said to three, "Stop!" or one said to two,
"Stop! I'm here!" then they're exempt. So that seems to point to
that the reason they're liable for the guy behind them is because
they had an opportunity to warn. Okay, so because they could've warned
they're liable, and if they did warn, they're exempt. Okay, so this
would seem to indicate that we say that you are considered responsible
to warn. You didn't have a chance to get up and you're
in the process of getting up, nevertheless, you should be warning the
guy behind you. Okay, so it says where were we? פטורים. pturim.
מאי לאו דלא היה להם לעמוד? mai lav d'lo haya lahem la'amod?
Are we not talking about a case that they didn't yet have
a chance to stand? And the liability comes because even though they
didn't have a chance to stand up, they should've been warning, which
is why the end of it talks about warning. לא שהיה להם
לעמוד. lo shehaya lahem la'amod. No.
The reason they're liable is because they had a chance to stand
up. So the גמרא Gemara says היה להם לעמוד. haya lahem la'amod.
So the גמרא Gemara says אבל לא היה להם לעמוד מאי פטור?
aval lo haya lahem la'amod mai patur? So if they didn't have
a chance to stand up, you'd say you'd be exempt even though
you could've warned? If that's true, אי הכי דקתני סיפא ואם הזהירו
זה את זה פטור, ei hachi d'katani seifa v'im hizhiru ze et
ze patur, where the end of it says if they warned they're
exempt, right? So that it should've ליתני וליפלוג בדידי. litni v'liflog bdidi.
It should've made a distinction within the case of having time to
stand up. במה דברים אמורים שהיה להם לעמוד. bameh devarim amurim shehaya
lahem la'amod. When these words are said, when they had a chance
to stand up. Are they liable if they could have stood up?
But לא היה להם לעמוד, aval lo hayah lahem la'amod, פטורים, pturim,
they're exempt even if they could have warned and they didn't warn.
That would be a big חידוש. chiddush. So the גמרא Gemara says
no, הא קמשמע לן, ha kamashma lan, this is telling you דאף
על גב דהיה להם לעמוד de'af al gav de'hayah lahem la'amod even
though they could have stood up and effectively removed the entire hazard,
and they didn't stand up, כי הזהיר זה את זה פטורים, ki
hizhir zeh et zeh pturim, they're nevertheless exempt if they warned, right?
You could have thought if you could have more removed yourself completely
and you were taking your sweet time and you just warned somebody,
that's not good enough. Right? Maybe we require if you have the
time to remove yourself, you had to remove yourself. We tell you
no, warning does suffice.
So although the, and you could check your emails while you're down,
and you could check your emails, no, that's probably, so well I
don't know, maybe if you're warning people, once you're warning them and
sending out a regular warning, maybe you can check your emails. Okay,
so okay, so anyway, you get your laptop to start proclaim, you
know, broadcasting a warning, okay anyway, so what it's saying is, although
the ברייתא braita sounds like the issue is did you have a
chance to warn and that presumably even when you're down you'll be
liable if you had a chance to warn, the גמרא Gemara. is
trying to defend רב יוחנן'ס Rav Yochanan's position and say no, there
is no liability until you have the opportunity to stand. While you're
in the process, while, you know, you don't have as much time
as you want, but while you are in the process, while you
have, while you're working on standing, okay, then you do not have
a responsibility to warn people. But even if you're taking more time
than you should, warning suffices. It's enough to warn people. But you're
not, don't begin to be liable until you've had a chance to
get up. That's at least רב יוחנן. Rav Yochanan. The other approach,
which I think obviously reads simpler, is the approach that you're liable
just because you could have warned even if you didn't have a
chance to stand. Okay, so that's one whole debate, if you could
have warned the person behind you, and among that we sort of
introduced this idea of multi-car pileup and this question about did I
have a right to stop in the first place, if I didn't
have a right to stop in the first place that creates greater
liability. Really, really fascinating. Now, and behind this in the background is
this idea that you need
liability, right? We're not saying אדם מועד לעולם, adam muad l'olam, and
we put out there three possibilities. Either you're a בור bor when
somebody trips on you and that's why you need liability, or you're
an אדם המזיק adam hamazik. and even an אדם המזיק adam hamazik,
needs liability and liability is the wrong word, needs negligence, or that
your negligence makes you into an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik, But anyway,
what's clear is that when somebody trips on you, you're only going
to be liable with a certain degree of negligence. Okay, that's presumed
about this. Now we're going to spend the rest of the דף,
daf, and there's a huge תוספות, Tosafot, and if you flip the
דף daf you'll see there's a huge רש״י, Rashi, and basically רש״י
Rashi and תוספות, Tosafot 80 percent of תוספות Tosafot. is just more
or less quoting רש״י, Rashi, okay, and all it's really doing is
trying to explain the case that the גמרא Gemara. is going to
be dealing with, okay, and just to show you a little bit
if you look at the עמוד ב, amud bet, look at the
left margin of the עמוד ב, amud bet, the far-left margin, it
says
עיין ברי״ף ובהרא״ש ובהרמ״ה ובמלחמות, ayen ba-Rif u'va-Rosh u'va-Ramah u'va-Milchamot, that's four
different ראשונים. rishonim. You don't see in the far right, I don't
know in your
דף, daf, you have פירושים אחרים. perushim acherim. So go look at
these four ראשונים rishonim for four completely different explanations of what the
גמרא Gemara. is talking about. Okay, so we're about to have a
little bit of fun in the next and the following cases in
the גמרא. Gemara Let's take a look. אמר מר amar mar says
the following. Okay, what? You got it? All right. Anyway, back to
the
גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבא amar Rava ראשון חייב בנזקי שני. rishon chayav
b'niskei sheni. In this case, one trips and two trips on one
and three trips on two, the first guy is חייב chayav in
the damages of the second guy, בין בנזקי גופו בין בנזקי ממונו,
bein b'niskei gufo bein b'niskei mamono, whether it's about the damages of
the body or the damages of the property. Okay, so here is
the first big question the ראשונים rishonim have. What do we mean?
What does that mean? Whether damage of money or damage of property?
So what do you think it means?
Did he rip his clothing
versus he broke his leg?
Whether guy number one broke guy number two's property or broke guy
number two's person, leg. Okay, what's another possible read, Charlie?
It is guy number one's body doing the damage or guy number...
Whether the guy number one's body damaged guy number two or whether
guy number one's property damaged guy number two, okay, that's the first
completely big sort of question mark about how to even parse the
words of the גמרא.
Gemara, It means people going on number two and number one.
Right. We are going to read this like רש״י. Rashi. Okay, רש״י
Rashi says, רש״י Rashi has a very nice, although רש״י Rashi also
changes the גרסא girsa of the גמרא Gemara, to be consistent with
his interpretation, but in terms of the printed text that we have,
רש״י Rashi has a very smooth read of the גמרא. Gemara. So
here's what רש״י Rashi is saying is, whether guy number one's person
or property damages guy number two. Now the difference is this focuses
us in on: is a person who is stationary in somebody tripping
over him, a בור bor, or an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. So
the difference is, if my body damages guy number two, I am
an אדם המזיק. adam hamazik. If my property damages guy number two,
the pot that I was carrying that broke and that guy damages
guy number two, that's a בור bor? because that's my property. Okay,
so let's read it.
Why would you read it the other way?
Because it doesn't continue to read throughout the גמרא, Gemara or if
it does, it raises issues. You can read תוספות. Tosafot תוספות Tosafot
gives you both reads of the גמרא, Gemara and if you read
the רי"ף Rif and the רמב"ן and the בעל המאור Baal HaMaor
and the רא"ש Rosh for three other explanations, or four other explanations.
Okay, okay, so ראשון חייב בנזקי שני. Rishon chayav benizkei sheni. The
first guy's liable for the damage to the second. בין בנזקי גופו
בין בנזקי ממונו, bein benizkei gufo bein benizkei mamono, whether his body
damaged guy number two or his property damaged guy number two. שני
חייב בנזקי שלישי, Sheni chayav benizkei shelishi, two is liable for guy
number three, בנזקי גופו, benizkei gufo, if his body damaged guy number
three, אבל לא בנזקי ממונו, aval lo benizkei mamono, but not if
his property damaged guy number three. So let's see why not. ממה
נפשך, ma nafshach, make up your mind, says the גמרא. Gemara. אי
נתקל פושע הוא, ei nitkal poshea hu, if the guy who tripped
is negligent, so שני נמי ליחייב, sheni nami lichayev, so let this
guy number two be liable fully for damage to guy number three.
Now, of course, the funny thing is right here, if guy number
one was negligent, it doesn't mean guy number two was negligent. You
might be negligent for tripping over your own two feet; you're not
negligent for tripping over the guy that just fell down in front
of you. Okay, doesn't matter. Anyway, we're not going to stick with
that. But the point is, if the second guy had negligence, let
him be חייב chayav whether it's his body or his property that
damages guy number three. אי נתקל לאו פושע הוא, ei nitkal lav
poshea hu, and if guy number two didn't have negligence, or nobody
who trips has negligence, אפילו ראשון נמי ליפטר, afilu rishon nami lipater,
let guy number one be exempt. Which the better question is, what
is the reason that guy number one is liable for his person
and his property, and the guy number two is only liable for
his person and not his property? That's basically the question. Let's see
what the answer is. So the גמרא Gemara. says, ראשון
ודאי פושע הוא. rishon vadai poshea hu. Guy number one is negligent.
You trip over your own two feet, נתקל פושע. nitkal poshea. Okay,
שני, sheni, the guy number two, אגופו מחייב, agufo michayev, you're liable
for your own person when somebody damages themselves on your person. דהוה
ליה למיקם ולא קם, de-hava lei lemeikam velo kam,
you should have stood up. Okay, like we've been saying. אממונו פטור,
ammono patur, you're exempt, guy number two, if your property damages guy
number three, דאמר ליה, de-amar lei, because he can say to guy
number three, האי בירא לאו אנא כריתיה, hai bira lav ana keriteya,
I didn't dig this well, my pot, right? That happened באונס. be-ones.
What does that mean? It means the following. I think we really
need some pictures now. Okay, waiting for the picture. Okay, guy number
one falls down, and here's his broken pot, here's his property, okay,
whoops, okay, so that's פושע. poshea. Got to put a number one.
What? Got to put a number one. Okay, so he's a פושע,
poshea, נתקל פושע. nitkal poshea. Okay, so he's a פושע. poshea. Here
he is. He's an אדם המזיק adam hamazik and this is a
בור bor that was created through פשיעה. peshia. So he's going to
be חייב chayav on either thing that happens to guy number two.
Okay, now, guy number
two, draw him here with a different color.
You have to draw him flying over.
I don't know what, whoa,
okay, I don't know, okay. Anyway, guy number two, okay, he is
an אונס. ones. Okay, he had... he tripped over guy number one.
Okay, that's not his fault. Will you tell me he's... why is
he נתקל?
nitkal? He is a נתקל, nitkal,
but normal נתקל פושע nitkal poshea means when you trip on your
own two feet. Okay, tripping over somebody, you're an אונס. ones. Okay,
so he's an אונס. ones. So this בור bor. is also made
באונס. be-ones. Everything is made באונס. be-ones. Okay, it starts off that
he's an אונס ones and he should totally be פטור. patur. But
then he had a chance to get up. So his initial... the
fall was באונס, be-ones, but then after one minute's time, after one
minute, הוה ליה למיקם hava lei lemeikam and he's a פושע. poshea.
So now he's responsible for somebody who trips on him. But should
he have also removed this בור? bor, This בור bor? was created
באונס, be-ones, so he's not liable for it. Now, what are you
supposed to say? Ah, but he had a minute, what should he
have done in that minute? He should have picked it up, gathered
it up. So what we're going to assume that once you have
a broken pitcher, you're מפקיר mafkir it. Okay, remember מפקיר נזקיו לאחר
נפילת
אונס?
mafkir nezikav le-achar nefilat
ones?
Yes, we assume you're מפקיר mafkir לאחר נפילה. le-achar nefila. So you
do never have to pick up your pieces. I did not make
this בור. bor. This בור bor got made באונס. be-ones. And after
that, I stopped being responsible. I was מפקיר mafkir it. So I
am liable for myself, but I am not liable for my בור.
bor Okay, so the first guy, everything was דפשיעה, de-peshia, is liable
for himself and his בור. bor, The second guy is liable for
himself because he should have stood up. He was initially it was
all באונס, be-ones, but
then... No, we presume, we presume. Why wouldn't the
first
guy be מפקיר mafkir for his?
He might have been, but he made it בפשיעה. b'p'shiah. You made
a בור bor. בפשיעה, b'p'shiah, it doesn't matter if you continue owning
it or not. It's like digging a well in רשות הרבים. reshut
harabbim. Okay, but if you didn't make the בור, bor. you're only
liable for not cleaning it up if you continue to own it.
What happens to the בור? bor.
What do you mean? Could have warned about this. It's not his
responsibility to warn about it. He didn't make it בפשיעה, b'p'shiah, he
didn't make it, he didn't make the hazard, and he wasn't supposed
to clean up the hazard, it's not his hazard.
Guy number three comes along and
gets damaged on this, nobody's responsible for
it.
Why should people, guy number three is still out then.
I understand, that happens sometimes, you get damaged and nobody has the
liability. Okay, that's the explanation. Yeah.
So according to the, this is רש"י's Rashi explanation. So, but it
still fits in with the גמרא Gemara that the first one is
חייב chayav בין בנזקי גופו בין בנזקי ממונו. bein b'nizkei gufo bein
b'nizkei mamono. Right.
He's חייב chayav for everything about number two. Right. Okay, so either
way it still fits in with the גמרא.
Gemara Right. Yeah, we're good. Okay, there's no problem. רש"י Rashi has
a good read of the גמרא.
Gemara And תוספות Tosafot says the same law.
No, no, don't start worrying about the other read, okay? We're not
going to confuse people, okay? Let's keep on going. So the גמרא
Gemara says like this. Okay. Okay. מיתיבי, Meiteivi, I'll ask you. כולם
חייבין. Kulam chayavin. We have a ברייתא braita that says about this
case, כולם חייבין על נזקי גופן ופטורין על נזקי ממונם. Kulam chayavin
al nizkei gufan u'pturin al nizkei mamonam. All the people, one through
three, are
all liable for the damage their body does, and they're all exempt
for the damage that their property does. Okay? We're going to consistently
read this as talking about, well, we're going to read it consistently,
okay? It's about the property, the damage that their body is doing,
the damage that their property is doing. Okay? כולם חייבין על נזקי
גופן ופטורין על נזקי ממונם. Kulam chayavin al nizkei gufan u'pturin al
nizkei mamonam.
So you see, everybody is exempt on their property. מאי לאו אפילו
ראשון? Mai lav afilu rishon? Doesn't it mean even guy one is
exempt for his property? Okay. No, לבר מראשון. L'var me'rishon. Everybody except
for number one. The גמרא Gemara says כולם. Kulam. It says everybody,
okay? There aren't so many people here, okay? There's one, two, and
three, so everybody presumably means everybody. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר
רב אדא בר אהבה כולם הניזקין. Amar Rav Adda bar Ahava, kulam
hanizakin. No, it means everybody who was damaged, okay? Not the first
guy. The first guy is the big damager, but all the guys
who tripped over him, they're all exempt for what their property did,
okay? Everybody that follows number one that trips as a result of
number one, they're all exempt. The גמרא Gemara, still isn't happy. היי
מאי? Hai mai? What are you talking about? אי אמרת בשלמא אפילו
ראשון, Ei amart bishlama afilu rishon, everybody, even number one, היינו דקתני
כולם. hainu d'tani kulam. It says כולם. kulam. אי אמרת לבר מראשון,
Ei amart l'var me'rishon, everybody except number one, מאי כולם? mai kulam?
ליתני הניזקין. Litni hanizakin. Say all those that were damaged are exempt
for their property, okay? By saying כולם, kulam, the גמרא's Gemara point
here is not just that the word כולם kulam means everybody, but
that it could have chosen a better word. It could have said
those that were damaged are exempt for their property. אלא, Ela, so
we've got a problem now. This is a very nice explanation, we
understand exactly what רבא Rava is saying, but it doesn't fit with
the ברייתא braita that says everybody is exempt for the damage their
property does. אלא אמר רבא, Ela amar Rava, rather רבא Rava says,
ראשון חייב בין בנזקי גופו דשני בין בנזקי ממונו דשני. Rishon chayav
bein b'nizkei gufo d'sheni bein b'nizkei mamono d'sheni. So רבא Rava changes
his claim because of the ברייתא. braita. ראשון חייב בין בנזקי גופו
דשני בין בנזקי ממונו דשני, Rishon chayav bein b'nizkei gufo d'sheni bein
b'nizkei mamono d'sheni, ושני חייב בנזקי שלישי בנזקי גופו אבל לא בנזקי
ממונו. v'sheni chayav b'nizkei shlishi b'nizkei gufo aval lo b'nizkei mamono. So
here, notice it spells out נזקי גופו דשני, nizkei gufo d'sheni, נזקי
ממונו דשני. nizkei mamono d'sheni. So now we are switching gears and
talking about the thing being damaged, not the thing doing the damage,
okay? So let's read this again. ראשון, Rishon, where were we? חייב
בין בנזקי גופו דשני בין בנזקי ממונו, Chayav bein b'nizkei gufo d'sheni
bein b'nizkei mamono, okay? Whether he, the person, damages guy number two's
person or damages guy number two's property, he's חייב. chayav. Why? Because
only an אדם המזיק adam hamazik. is חייב chayav by damaging property.
A בור bor. that damages property is פטור, patur, everybody remember that?
So the ראשון rishon is חייב chayav for this because the ראשון
rishon is an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik okay? So he's חייב chayav
whether you damage a person's person or property. And the second guy,
here's number three who trips over guy number two. Oh, I don't
know why I'm drawing it like that. Anyway, the second guy is
חייב, chayav, where were we? שני חייב בנזקי שלישי בנזקי גופו אבל
לא בנזקי ממונו. Sheni chayav b'nizkei shlishi b'nizkei gufo aval lo b'nizkei
mamono. He's חייב chayav only on this guy's person, but not, here's
this guy's property, okay, but not. on this guy's property. Okay. What's
the reason? What we are saying is a completely different statement we're
making now. The first guy is an אדם המזיק adam hamazik, and
חייב chayav if he damages this guy or this guy's property. The
second guy is a בור. bor. And as a בור, bor he's
חייב chayav only if the person gets damaged on him, but not
if the person's property gets damaged on him. Now, what is the
difference? Why? Here's the question we were asking. You're stationary, somebody trips
over you. Are you an אדם המזיק adam hamazik, or are you
a בור? bor, And basically we're saying it differs between the first
guy and the second guy. The first guy's an אדם המזיק, adam
hamazik the second guy is a בור. bor. What's the difference? And
the basic difference is, okay, the degree of negligence. All right? And
I think that the only way to explain this is what I
said before, because why should negligence determine what category you're in? But
what negligence determines is agency. Okay? So, if I tripped and let's
say I was פושע poshea in my tripping, okay, or you know,
or even if I wasn't פושע, poshea, I certainly was close to
being פושע, poshea, okay, and then I could have warned or all
those things. So I certainly have a, you know, have a certain
degree of פשיעה pshiah here, more than the guy behind me. I
mean, the guy behind me maybe could have also warned, but he
certainly had a lot less negligence in tripping over me. He was
much more of an אונס. oness. Okay? So because I have more
פשיעה, pshiah, it's more considered to be—I would frame this, רש״י Rashi
doesn't spell this out, but this is how I would frame this—as
more like my act. I am making... there's more agency, right? I've
more chosen to be here, and therefore it's like I'm a מזיק
mazik on the people that come behind me. It's like I'm active.
Whereas there, you just tripped and you're completely blameless. Now, you certainly
need a degree of negligence. You wouldn't be חייב chayav on בור
bor if you remained אונס. oness. Right? Everybody gets that? If you—if
he tripped and he had no opportunity to warn number three, he'd
be פטור. patur. Right? For to be חייב chayav for בור bor
you need פשיעה. pshiah. So we are assuming that he could have
warned him. But even though he could have warned him, okay, and
there's a degree of negligence, it's not enough negligence to make it—he
still tripped, it started as an accident. He could have warned, maybe
he couldn't have gotten up, maybe he only could have warned. It's
not enough to view it as though he is like actively staying
there and doing something to the other guy. He just is negligent
a little bit more in the abstract. So he has negligence for
his בור, bor but this guy who shouldn't have tripped in the
first place, this guy is act—and you know, and could have warned,
he's considered to more have agency and more be an אדם המזיק.
adam hamazik Okay? So they all have negligence or they wouldn't be
חייב, chayav, but this guy that is more to blame for the
initial tripping, he's an אדם המזיק, adam hamazik and this guy who
is just a בור. bor? Yes, as רש״י Rashi says—this guy's a
בור. bor, Yes, that's what רש״י Rashi says it explicitly. You want
to see רש״י Rashi saying it? We can read the words in
רש״י. Rashi. Correct. So I'll read the key line in רש״י. Rashi.
רש״י Rashi says like this: So first of all, when רש״י Rashi
is explaining the previous גמרא Gemara that was an אדם adam המזיק,
if you look down six lines in the wide lines of רש״י,
Rashi, this was the earlier interpretation of רש״י. Rashi. רש״י Rashi says
at the beginning, like four words in, רש״י Rashi says: כגופו לא
משוינן ליה דין בור. K'gufo lo mashvinan lei din bor. Okay? We
wouldn't turn a person's body into a בור. bor? But in this
interpretation of the גמרא, Gemara רש״י Rashi says, if you go one,
two, three, four, five, six, seven, nine lines down, the line that
starts with לעמוד, do people see that word? It says הוי ליה
לעמוד. Havai lei la'amod. The first guy should have stood. אבל שני
אפילו היה לו לעמוד, Aval sheni afilu haya lo la'amod, although the
second guy should have stood, because if he didn't—if he didn't have
to stand, he wouldn't have any פשיעה, pshiah, he'd be completely exempt.
לא מחייב כולי האי כראשון. Lo mechayev kulei hai k'rishon. He's not
as liable as the first guy. דראשון הוי פושע טפי משני. D'rishon
havai poshea teifi m'sheni. The first guy was more negligent, he tripped
in the first place. הלכך ראשון ודאי הוי מזיק. Hilkach rishon vadai
havai mazik. The first guy's an אדם adam המזיק. ושני מסתייע טפי
שאם עשיתהו לגופו בור. V'sheni mista-ei t'fu-ei she-im asiseihu legufei bor. If
you define his body as a בור. bor וחייב בנזקי גופו של
שלישי אבל לא בנזקי ממונו. V'chayav b'nizkei gufo shel shlishi aval lo
b'nizkei mamono. So רש״י Rashi says that. He had more negligence, he's
an אדם המזיק, he had less negligence, he's a בור. bor But
the question is like: What does that mean? Like, who cares? Negligence
or not negligence. You're one or the other. And I would say
no, if you tripped and fell and you're passive and somebody trips
over you, to make you into an אדם המזיק, we have to
define your presence as an active being present, as agency, okay? And
therefore with more negligence it's like you're doing an act of damaging
the guy you're staying there. Here, you're not seen as much as
doing an act and therefore you're a בור bor. and not an
אדם המזיק. Yes, so he then takes it one step down. So
the first guy's בור, bor right? The first guy's an אדם המזיק.
No, but I'm saying the first guy's stuff that broke is now
a בור. bor, We're going to get to that. Okay. Yeah, right.
That would be מפקיר נזקיו לאחר פשיעה, mafkir nezakav le'achar pshiah, אונס
oness or מקיעה m'ki-ah or whatever, and that would have the relevant
laws. And then, but the... The second guy's trap, second guy presumably
be מפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילת אונס mafkir nezikav l'achar nefilat ones and
he'd be פטור. patur. Okay. Right. So the second guy's not liable
for damages anything. Like the second guy's בור bor. damages somebody else's
body. Correct. He'd be completely פטור. patur. Yeah, if it's מפקיר נזקיו
לאחר נפילת אונס, mafkir nezikav l'achar nefilat ones, correct. If—if נתקל פושע,
if nitkas poshea, which is what presumably we're assuming, presumably. Okay, but
let's take a look at what the גמרא Gemara. says. Okay. Okay,
now. בין בנזקי שני ושני חייב בנזקי שלישי ושלישי בנזקי גופו ולא
בנזקי ממונו. bein b'nizkei sheni v'sheni chayav b'nizkei shelishi v'shelishi b'nizkei gufo
lo b'nizkei mamono. מאי טעמא דהוה ליה בור? mai taama d'hava lei
bor? Now, אבל aval because this—ולא מצינו בור שחייב בו את הכלים.
v'lo matzinu bor she'chiyav bo et hakelim. Okay, he's a—this is, his
body is exempt on this guy's vessels because he's a בור bor.
and בור bor? is exempt on כלים. kelim. Okay, now the גמרא
Gemara says "One minute, הני ניחא לשמואל דאמר כל תקלה בור הוא?"
hani nicha l'Shmuel d'amar kol takala bor hu? Can you say a
person is a בור? bor. So, remember the debate of רב ושמואל.
Rav v'Shmuel. שמואל Shmuel was a בור, bor. for sure. Sorry, yeah,
right, אין בור ירא חטא ein bor yerei cheit or whatever, fine.
So if a person—so can a person be a בור? bor So
remember there's a debate of רב ושמואל. Rav v'Shmuel. If you own—is
a בור bor only something that you don't own? Right, remember they
had the אבדת סכינו ומשאו avda d'sakina massa'o your knapsack ברשות הרבים
b'reshut harabim if you still own it, for רב Rav it's a
שור. shor. Okay, so if for רב you—it can't be a בור
bor unless it's הפקר, hefker, then you can never be a בור.
bor Okay, you have to be something's—right? A בור bor starts as
something that's הפקר. hefker. So הני ניחא לשמואל דאמר כל תקלה בור
הוא? hani nicha l'Shmuel d'amar kol takala bor hu? For שמואל Shmuel
says that any hazard is a בור, bor a person can be
a בור. bor. אלא רב דאמר אי אפקריה אינו לאו, ella Rav
d'amar ee afkrei iney lo lo, only if you're מפקיר mafkir something
it's a בור. bor מאי איכא למימר? mai ika l'meimar? What can
you say? Okay, how can you say that the person is a
בור? bor All right, so the גמרא Gemara says no, לעולם כדאמר
מעיקרא, le'olam k'd'amar me'ikara, fine. Go back to what we were saying
before. Go back to the idea that—that the earlier interpretation, which was—I
like this one too, it gets to the question of if a
person is a בור. bor, Go back to the earlier interpretation, okay,
which is you're a, you know, that you are basically a—what was
it? You—everybody maybe is an אדם המזיק or whatever, and the difference
is what's the status of the stuff that fell. This is מפקיר
נזקיו לאחר נפילת פשיעה, mafkir nezikav l'achar nefilat peshiah, and this is
מפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילת אונס. mafkir nezikav l'achar nefilat ones. Okay, if
that's true, but what do you do about the fact that the
ברייתא Beraita says everybody is exempt for the damage that their objects
do? Okay, and this guy we said is liable for the damage
that his objects do. לעולם כדאמר מעיקרא ודקשיא לך כולם חייבין, le'olam
k'd'amar me'ikara v'd'kashya lach k'ulanu chayavin, that they're all obligated on what
their body does—actually it should have said כולם פטורין kulanu paturin and
they're all exempt on what their property does. So תרגמה רב אדא
בר אהבה קמיה דרבינא שהוזקו כלים בכלים. targema Rav Adda bar Ahavah
kamei d'Ravina she'huzzku kelim b'kelim. Ah, when we say they're all exempt
on what their property does and they're חייב chayav for what they
do, is we're talking only about when they're damaging vessels. So okay,
so this guy is a—what? I guess so. So this guy is,
okay, so everybody is essentially a case of היה לו לעמוד, haya
lo la'amod, so they're all let's say an אדם המזיק. So everybody
is liable for if the other guy's vessels break on them because
they all should have stood up and they're all אדם המזיק and
they're all liable for hurting the person behind them. But they're all—and
they're all exempt if their vessels break the other guy's vessels because
their vessels are a בור. bor And a בור is פטור בכלים.
patur b'kelim. Of course, that's a very boring read of the ברייתא.
Beraita. Of course their vessels are a בור and a בור is
פטור—what? patur Boring? I didn't mean that. Anyway, but I'm serious. Like
it's like you're not—you're just telling me a general—a standard הלכה. halakha.
Oh, by the way, of course! No, whether an אדם is a
בור or an אדם המזיק, that's an interesting question. The fact that
their broken pot is at most a בור and they're exempt because
it's כלים בכלים, בור בכלים, kelim b'kelim, bor b'kelim, of course that's
true. But anyway that's what—that's how we're reading it, okay? So what
did we learn? So we don't learn anything. Maybe we learned that
I don't know, we learned—we learned—we learned—we learned that היה לו לעמוד.
hayah lo l’amod? Okay, maybe we learned that a person who falls
and his היה לו לעמוד is an אדם המזיק, okay? But the
earlier explanation was really interesting because it said whether you're an אדם
המזיק or a בור might depend on your degree of negligence. If
he didn't have enough time then he'd be פטור, patur, is that
what we're saying? If he didn't have enough time, well certainly these
guys would be פטור, patur, this guy we haven't really figured out
whether נתקל פושע nitkas poshea or not, right. Okay, so that's basically
it. What we didn't actually explain was how the other read, which
was talking whatever, dealt with... with why כולם פטורין kulanu paturin by
the כלים, kelim, 'cause the other read basically was assuming—the other read
was all about, right remember the other read was are you חייב
chayav for this or are you חייב chayav for this and not
for that, right? 'Cause here you're an אדם and here you're a
בור. So in that case, we were assuming that נתקע nitka was
אונס, ones, the whole problem was was היה לו לעמוד, okay? And
that was going on, but because נתקל nitkal was אונס, ones, everybody
was not responsible for the בור that they created, for their vessels,
because it was מפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילה אונס. mafkir nezekav l’achar nefilah
ones. So that was that previous read of the ברייתא. Braitah. They’re
all liable for what their body does; their body is either a
בור or an אדם המזיק based on degree of negligence. Remember that
read? That this was an אדם and this was a בור, based
on degree of negligence they’re all חייב chayav for what their body
does, but they’re all פטור patur for what their vessels do because
it was מפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילה אונס. mafkir nezekav l’achar nefilah ones.
That was how that read worked. This final read is much less
interesting in terms of why you’re פטור patur on the vessels. But
again, the really interesting question is on the one hand it’s a
simple application of מפקיר נזקיו לאחר נפילה אונס. mafkir nezekav l’achar nefilah
ones. Are you a פושע, poshea, are you היה לו לעמוד? No
new ideas. The really interesting new idea that was introduced is: are
you an אדם המזיק or בור when you could have gotten up?
And רש״י Rashi says that might depend on your degree of negligence.
Okay, last line in the גמרא. Gemara Okay. אמר מר: Amar Mar:
אם מחמת ראשון נפלו כולם ראשון חייב בנזקי כולם. im machmat rishon
nafalu kulan rishon chayav b’neezikay kulam. If they fell because of the
first guy, he’s liable. And again, the גמרא’s Gemara reading this not
that the second and third were not negligent, but it’s still the
same scenario, one falls over one, two over two, etc. It’s the
גמרא’s—that Gemara would have been an interesting scenario: you fell over the
guy in front of you, but he didn’t have a chance to
stand, it was all the first guy’s fault and the first guy
pays for everybody. גמרא Gemara doesn’t read it like that. The גמרא
reads it that they all fell over the first guy. Okay, so
the גמרא says היכי נפל, heichi nafal, how did they fall? רב
פפא אמר: Rav Pappa amar: דפסקא לאורכא כשילדא. d’paska l’orkah k’shilda. He
was sort of, you know, spread across the road like basically רש״י
Rashi says like a carcass, okay, so his whole body or רש״י
Rashi says maybe something he was carrying, his whole body was spread
along the width of the road, so everybody tripped over the first
guy. Okay, there you go. Now רב זביד אמר: Rav Zevid amar:
כחוטרא דסמיותא, k’chutra d’samyusa, like the staff of a blind person. Now
what is the difference? Right? רש״י Rashi says it’s a—maybe it’s a—I
mean, it just sounds like two colorful illustrations. תוספות Tosafot has a
brilliant read. תוספות Tosafot says here is—I know those are—that was a
really good—those were really good pictures, weren’t they? Especially—תוספות Tosafot said, anyway,
yeah, the colors were helpful, wasn’t it? Okay, תוספות Tosafot, said, you’re
at an אלכסון, alaxon, an angle. And because you’re at an angle,
this is guy number one. No, which explanation are you picking? The
second one, the guy who’s like the staff of a blind person.
Okay, he’s like an angle. This is guy number one. Guy number
two comes along and he trips over guy number one. Okay, so
guy number three who’s walking here, right, he says, 'Oh, that guy
must have tripped over something way in front.' So he’s—he doesn’t realize
at this stage, right, it’s all across, you know, this is—like, you
know, he’s here and he says, 'I don’t have to be careful
yet, whatever that guy tripped over is like two feet ahead of
me.' Okay? And he doesn’t realize that the—at an angle. So the
reason what this is saying is that if the guy was completely
horizontal, then it’s not guy number one’s fault. You should have seen
guy number two that had fallen down. Don't blame me for tripping
over me, you saw guy number two was on the ground. But
if he’s at an angle, even though I saw guy number two
on the ground, I didn’t realize that the hazard was closer to
me than it was to him. Okay, so that’s how come everybody
could be falling over me but I can’t say to you, 'Look,
you saw the other guy on the ground, you should have been
careful,' because if I was at an angle, you didn’t know to
be careful earlier on and therefore... All right, I’m sure that matters
too. We will end with this. All right. It does use אלכסון.
alaxon. I don’t know why, according—it’s a very creative read of תוספות,
but again, I don’t know why the גמרא wouldn’t have just said
that more explicitly. Thank you.